Preliminary Guide to the Stanhope Bayne-Jones Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Stanhope Bayne-Jones papers
1935-1972
MS 1271
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
Memoirs, correspondence, reports, and printed matter largely reflecting Stanhope Bayne-Jones' service as dean of the Yale School of Medicine, 1935-1940. The most significant part of the papers are his memoirs in the form of a transcript of an oral history interview conducted by Dr. Harlan Phillips for the National Library of Medicine in 1966. In the interviews, Bayne-Jones describes his education, his service in World War I, his research and his career. Included also are papers relating to his portrait which was installed in the library of the School of Medicine in 1959.
Bayne-Jones, Stanhope, 1888-1970
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale University Historical Medical LIbrary, 1980.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This unprocessed collection contains papers pertaining to Stanhope Bayne-Jones. The most interesting portion of the collection consists of Bayne-Jones's memoirs. These are in the form of a five-volume mimeographed copy of typed transcripts of an oral history elicited by Dr. Harlan Phillips from Bayne-Jones for the National Library of Medicine in 1966. In the interviews Bayne-Jones describes his education and service in World War I, his research, colleagues, and his career.
The collection also contains several items of Bayne-Jones's correspondence about the report of the Dean of the Yale School of Medicine to the President of the University and about the Scientific Research Bill of 1937. In addition, there is a copy of a report about medical research produced for the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare by a committee of which Bayne-Jones was the chairman.
The remaining papers, approximately one third of the collection, consist of correspondence, financial records, notes, and printed matter of the Bayne-Jones Portrait Committee. This Yale School of Medicine group was charged with having a portrait of Bayne-Jones painted for the Historical Medicine Library, and the papers deal with fund-raising and with the official unveiling of the portrait on December 11, 1959.
Biographical / Historical
Stanhope Bayne-Jones (1888-1970): bacteriologist; professor at Johns Hopkins Hospital, 1922-1923; at University of Rochester, 1923-1932; director of Rochester Health Bureau Labs, 1926-1932; professor at Yale University School of Medicine, 1932-1947, dean of School of Medicine, 1935-1940; served in Surgeon General's Office, 1942-1946; administrator, Army Epidermiological Board, 1944-1946; served with several foundations, 1937-1941, 1948-; president, Joint Administration Board of N.Y. Hospital-Cornell Medical Center, 1947-1953; consultant to U.S. Army and U.S. government, 1952-; active in many societies and associations.
Medicine; World War, 1914-1918; Autobiographies (documents); Oral histories (document genres); Bacteriologists; Educators; Bayne-Jones, Stanhope, 1888-1970; Phillips, Harlan B. (Harlan Buddington), 1920-1979; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. School of Medicine
- Inventory
  - Dean of the School of Medicine: report to the president of Yale University; correspondence, 1935-1936 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence concerning the Scientific Research Bill, H.R. 7939, 1937 (Box 1)
  - The Advancement of Medical Research and Education Through the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, Office of the Secretary, Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, 1958 June 27 (Box 1)
  - Bayne-Jones Portrait Committee, Yale University School of Medicine: correspondence, financial records, printed matter, 1958-1972 (Box 1)
  - Memoirs of Stanhope Bayne-Jones
    - Vol I: Introduction, Index, Transcripts of Documents, 1966 April-July (Box 1)
    - Vol II-IV: Transcripts of oral history, 1966 April-July (Box 1)
    - Vol. V: Bayne-Jones Collection Catalogue, 1966 April-July (Box 1)
    - Related papers, 1967, 1971 (Box 1)